<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/css" href="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/code/pfs.css"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Davids reserve and rescue in a sermon preached before the honourable the House of Commons, on the fifth of November, 1644 / by Charles Herle ...</title>
            <author>Herle, Charles, 1598-1659.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 59KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 14 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2016-02">2016-02 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A70212</idno><idno type="EEBO-CITATION">11913823</idno>
  <idno type="VID">50869</idno>
  <idno type="EEBO-PROQUEST">2248538976</idno>
  
            <idno type="STC">Wing H1554</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R12675</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">11913823</idno>
            <availability><p>This keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above is co-owned by the
    institutions providing financial support to the Early English Books Online Text Creation
    Partnership. This text is available for reuse, according to the terms of <ref target="https://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/"> Creative Commons 0 1.0 Universal
    licence</ref>. The text can be copied, modified, distributed and performed, even for commercial
    purposes, all without asking permission.</p></availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online text creation partnership.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt><relatedItem type="facs" target="https://data.historicaltexts.jisc.ac.uk/view?pubId=eebo-e"/>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A70212)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 50869)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 231:E19, no 17)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Davids reserve and rescue in a sermon preached before the honourable the House of Commons, on the fifth of November, 1644 / by Charles Herle ...</title>
                  <author>Herle, Charles, 1598-1659.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[20] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed for John Wright ...,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1644/45 [i.e. 1645]</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in Thomason Collection, British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,363 texts created during Phase 1 of the project have been released into the public domain as of 1 January 2015. Anyone can now take and use these texts for their own purposes, but we respectfully request that due credit and attribution is given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Full documentation of the original data capture process is available from the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.
   All versions of the texts are now archived and freely available for download. See <ref target="https://textcreationpartnership.org/faq/#faq05">the TCP Download FAQ</ref>
   for detailed information. The TEI P5 versions are also freely available from the <ref target="https://github.com/textcreationpartnership">TCP Github repository</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp" matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)" replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char" matchPattern="(.+)" replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term type="topical_term">Sermons, English --  17th century.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2014-04 </date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images </change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-08 </date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum </label>Sampled and proofread </change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-08 </date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited </change>
         <change>
            <date>2015-03 </date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion </change>
      <change><date>2021-05 </date><label>lb</label>TEI P5 conversion </change></revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="order">
            <pb facs="tcp:50869:1"/>
            <head>Die Martis, <hi>6.</hi> Novemb. <hi>1644.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>ORdered by the Commons Assem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bled in Parliament, That M. <hi>Nicoll</hi> and M. <hi>Ashurst,</hi> doe from this House give thanks to M. <hi>Herle,</hi> for the great pains he took in his Sermon on the Fifth of No<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vember, at the intreaty of the said Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mons, at <hi>Margarets Westminster,</hi> and to desire him to print his Sermon; and it is Ordered, That none shall presume to print his Sermon, but whom the said M. <hi>Herle</hi> shall authorize under his hand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>writing.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>H. Elsynge, Cler. Parl. D. Com.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="appointment">
            <p>I appoint <hi>John Wright</hi> to print my Sermon.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>CHARLES HERLE.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:50869:1"/>
            <p>DAVIDS Reserve, and Rescue, IN A SERMON, PREACHED Before the Honourable, the House of COMMONS, <hi>On the Fifth of November.</hi> 1644.</p>
            <p>By CHARLES HERLE, Pastor of <hi>Winwick</hi> in <hi>Lancashire.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Published by Order of the said House.</hi>
            </p>
            <q>
               <p>
                  <bibl>
                     <hi>Psal.</hi> 52.1.</bibl> Why boastest thou thy selfe thou tyrant, that thou canst do mischief? whereas the goodnesse of God endureth yet daily.</p>
               <p>
                  <bibl>
                     <hi>Prov.</hi> 17.17.</bibl> A friend loveth at all times, and a brother is borne for adversity.</p>
            </q>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed for <hi>John Wright,</hi> in the Old-Baily. 1645.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:50869:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:50869:2"/>
            <head>To the Honourable, the House of Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mons assembled in PARLIAMENT.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">A</seg>N honest Sermon, I acknowledge (as an ancient Writer observes) hath much of the miracle in it, though but a <hi>few ba<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ley loaves,</hi> yet may it <hi>feed many thousands:</hi> It may be our Saviour (more then once) <hi>closed</hi> his Sermons with such <hi>miracles,</hi> as so many <hi>emblemes</hi> of this multi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plying <hi>bread of life.</hi> However, it seems your care is (as that of his) that <hi>the broken meat be gathered up too, that none be lost,</hi> whereby others might be afterwards fed too. But for this (rather <hi>pulse</hi> then) <hi>bread</hi> here againe presented you, it hath little or nothing to commend it to publike use, more then (toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther with your Order) the solemnity of the Office you were pl<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sed to put upon it. That first great Fifth of November hath been so fruitfull to you ever since,<note place="margin">Qui non est gratus datis, non est dig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nus dandis.</note> and multiplyed into so many more, (I meane dayes of deliverance) that forgetfulnesse could not but prove a forfeiture: thankfulnesse is the best tenure, gives the surest title to new mercies: if <hi>hope</hi> be (as the Apostle speaks) the <hi>best Anchor,</hi> gratitude (questionlesse) is the strongest <hi>Cable</hi> to fasten it by; you must expect still to stand in need of more deliverances: the same brood of enemies that then durst venture but on an <hi>undermining,</hi> dare now attempt an open <hi>bat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tery.</hi> Nor are they without their Pioners too, still at worke, and now busier then ever, in digging vaults, such as may reach from <hi>Oxford, Rome, Hell,</hi> to <hi>Westminster,</hi> and there to blow up (if possible) the better <hi>Foundations</hi> of your <hi>Houses,</hi> their <hi>Liberties</hi> and <hi>Priviledges.</hi> Things of a <hi>morall</hi> nature,
<pb facs="tcp:50869:3"/> their very <hi>essence</hi> lies in their <hi>ends,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Finis habet rationem formae in mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ralibus. Proprieta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tum remotio est naturae negatio.</note> which if they fall short of, they fall to worse then nothing: their qualifications <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e not onely the ornaments, but the props of their existence, their being such, or such, is many times of more concernment then their being or not being: Parliaments are of this nature, they are essentiated, centred, and secured in their beings by their being such as they should be, <hi>.i. free.</hi> In <hi>Davids</hi> time Gods enemies found no way so ready to <hi>destroy Gods Law,</hi> as to <hi>imagine mischiefe as a law</hi> against it: could your enemies but once <hi>ima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gine their mischiefe</hi> into a <hi>law,</hi> give it a Parliamentary san<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction, and destroy your Priviledges <hi>cum privilegio,</hi> they would not need any more to spend their powder in blowing up the <hi>walls</hi> of your Houses, it would much better serve their turne, at the <hi>doores</hi> to catch, and awe, and watch your Votes into a lamenesse and servility, and (with <hi>Issachar</hi>) a <hi>willingnesse, out of the love of rest, to bow the shoulder to beare and become a ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vant to tribute.</hi> This <hi>Sampson</hi> (his haire once off, and his eyes out) would serve excellently to grinde in a Court-Horse-<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ill: Parliaments (like Diamonds) are not so easily broken with ham<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mers or swords either, as they are cut to peeces with their owne dust, when once they should be ground thereinto by tyrannie. But I presume not (as the manner is) to present you with an Epistle of advice, when you call but for the Sermon, or to presse you with pragmatick considerations and rules for <hi>peace</hi> or <hi>justice,</hi> as if you had forgotten the businesse you were met about: I would not give you cause to say (with him in the Epigrammatist) —<hi>Quod pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Martial.</note>
               <hi>da mihi, non peto consilium:</hi> I onely pray that you m<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>y keep many Fifths of November, to the joy (amongst the rest) of</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Your humble servant, in and for the Lord Christ, CHARLES HERLE.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:50869:3"/>
            <head>DAVIDS RESERVE AND RESCUE: IN A SERMON, Preached before the Honourable, the House of COMMONS, on the Fifth of November. 1644.</head>
            <epigraph>
               <q>
                  <bibl>2 SAM. 21.16, 17.</bibl>
                  <p>Then Ishbibenob, which was of the sons of the Gyant, (the weight of whose speare weighed <hi>300.</hi> shekels of brasse in weight) he being girt with a new sword, thought to have slain David.</p>
                  <p>But Abishai the sonne of Zerviah succoured him.</p>
               </q>
            </epigraph>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>His Chapter begins with one circle, or round of providence, and concludes with another; it begins with a great judgement, upon a great oppression, a three yeares Fami<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e upon the Land for <hi>Sauls</hi> oppression of the Gibeonites; next, a restitution of plenty and peace to it, upon the execution of 7. of his sons; execu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of justice removes that judgement that oppression hath bred, as if heaven it selfe would hold out this lesson to us, written in its owne <hi>brasse,</hi> that which <hi>Sin</hi> makes it, That <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e cruelty on earth is fitly punished by se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verity
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:50869:4"/> from heaven, so this severity of heaven in <hi>vengeance</hi> is best re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moved by a like impartiall severitie on earth in <hi>Iustice;</hi> one severity calls upon and ecchoes to another, earthly cruell severity, in oppres<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sion, calls upon heavens just severitie in affliction; and if that be not ag<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ine answered by another severity of earth in justice, it remaines still guilty and obnoxious to that just severity of heaven.</p>
            <p>And, as the Chapter begins with this revolution of, first, a great oppression, and then a great judgement; next, an execution of ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stice and then a removeall of the judgement; so ends it with one no lesse remarkable neither <hi>viz.</hi> of <hi>enemies,</hi> and <hi>warres, victories,</hi> and <hi>praises,</hi> inveterate <hi>enemies, Philistins,</hi> will be suppressed no way but by <hi>warres,</hi> such <hi>warres</hi> against such <hi>enemies,</hi> never end, though through many difficulties, but in certaine <hi>victories;</hi> and those <hi>victo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries</hi> should never end but in cheerfull praises to their Authour, <hi>They all fell by the hands of</hi> David—and <hi>then spake</hi> David <hi>the words of this Song</hi>—the old <hi>Parallell</hi> between <hi>Papists</hi> and <hi>Philistins,</hi>
               <note place="margin">2 <hi>Sam.</hi> 22.1</note> time is every day a drawing out to a further length of Allegory: <hi>Papists</hi> have ever been the <hi>Philistins</hi> of our <hi>Israel,</hi> they would not <hi>allow us any weapons,</hi> no not those of prayers and teares, <hi>but out of their Forge;</hi> they would faine by <hi>Covenant put out our right eyes</hi> too, our eyes of faith, and still (as the Text here) <hi>moreover the Philistins had yet againe warres with Israel</hi>—all their former attempts and defeats at <hi>Gilgall</hi> and <hi>Elah</hi> (with the rest) cannot lay their rancour, but to it they will againe; neither with these Philistins of ours, hath their <hi>Armado</hi> or <hi>Powder-plot</hi> given vent enough to their malice; <hi>moreover</hi> still we see <hi>new warres with Israel;</hi> whilst that <hi>hell</hi> hath a <hi>Forge</hi> above ground, and <hi>Rome</hi> a <hi>Factorage</hi> here in <hi>England,</hi> wee must look for no other.</p>
            <p>In this Philistin warre with <hi>Israel</hi> (this I meane in the Text) <hi>David</hi> is distressed, <hi>and waxes faint:</hi> The best <hi>Cause,</hi> (we see) as well as <hi>Champion,</hi> may be reduced to straights, we must not measure either the cause, or Gods assistance of it, by every distresse or danger it may fall into, God will teach us our dependence, and somtime our improvidence, as well as thankfulnesse by his supplies; and so jea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lous is hee over us, as he thinks not we are enough his, if he make us not to owe him our safeties, our lives often over: should our <hi>M<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="4 letters">
                     <desc>••••</desc>
                  </gap>
               </hi> be alwaies at Full, we should forget that it borrowed its light from the <hi>Sun,</hi> sometimes he will let his hand slip, that we may get faster hold of it, Gods <hi>actions</hi> are no bounds or measures of his <hi>attributes</hi>
               <pb n="3" facs="tcp:50869:4"/> he doth never put forth all his strength, somtimes little or none, his power it is alwaies infinite, the application of it is contracted and scantled, somtimes withdrawn and suspended, according to the mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sure or indisposednesse of our narrow capacities for receipt, as wee may not presumptuously conclude of his judgements he hath not, therfore he will not strike; so, nor despondently of his succours,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Esa.</hi> 59.1.</note> he doth not, therefore he cannot, he will not relieve; <hi>his arme is never shortned, nor his care heavy,</hi> it is our <hi>iniquities that hide them,</hi> it is our carnall hearts that will not let us see him, no longer then we feel him, otherwise we should never faile, (as <hi>David</hi> here) of some <hi>Abi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bishai</hi> or other, as a seasonable <hi>reserve</hi> at hand in all our straights and <hi>faintings,</hi> nor in this straight of <hi>David</hi> is the Philistine lesse at hand then <hi>Abishai, then Ishbibenob which was of the Sons of the Gyant, thought to have slaine David;</hi> whatever we do, our Philistines (wee see) will be sure to take their opportunities; and let slip no straight of ours, or advantage of their owne, I warrant them, they know an advantage, (in war especially) not taken, is not onely lost, but given, they will not shew their teeth before they be ready to bite, but doe well know how to improve and watch an occasion into a surprisall: <hi>Then Ishbibenob.</hi> The words of the Text containe a brief story of a war, wherein the parts are foure:</p>
            <p n="1">1. The <hi>Champion</hi> or Combatant <hi>Ishbibenob, who was of the Sons of the Gyant.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="2">2. His furniture of warre or <hi>Ammunition, and appointment, the weight of whose Speare weighed—he being girt with a new Sword.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="3">3. His <hi>Designe</hi> or <hi>Councell</hi> of warre, <hi>he thought to have slaine David.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="4">4. His defeat or disappointment, <hi>but Abishai the Son of Zervi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ah succoured him.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>In the first part we have 4. particulars, the 1. <hi>Stature:</hi> 2. <hi>Name:</hi> 3. <hi>Lynage:</hi> 4. <hi>Fraternity</hi> of this <hi>Combatant:</hi> all in the Text.</p>
            <p>For the first, the <hi>Stature</hi> or quality of the man, he was a <hi>Gyant.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>A <hi>Gyant,</hi> should we here run out into all those <hi>Romanses</hi> that fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bulous antiquity hath storyed of <hi>Gyants,</hi> our discourse would be as vast and monstrous as they themselves were, it may serve our turne that the Scriptures frequently make mention of them, and give them by way of a double anticipation or countercharme against both what they thought of themselves in life, and others thought of
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:50869:5"/> them afterward, <hi>Rapha .i.</hi> dead men, foreseeing that men would make them Gods after their death, and therefore calling them dead men even while they lived.</p>
            <p>The modestest conjecture that I find, how such became so frequent in former times, (laying aside as ridiculous, that the Divell should be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>get them upon Witches) is that in those ruder times of the World, when as yet <hi>Politics</hi> or frames of government were not erect<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>d, and strength of body only prevailed, men did generally aff<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ct nothing so much as vastnesse of strength and stature, and therefore chose their wives, or such on whom they desired to have children with an eye specially to their bulke, some gather as much from that of <hi>Gen.</hi> 6.4. where it is said, <hi>The sons of God saw the daughters of men, that they were faire,</hi> or, (as they would have it read) <hi>large, and they bare them children which became mighty men of renowne;</hi> now as wee see in Boares and Bulls, (with other like creatures) otherwise by nature or custome tame, yet through vastnesse of bulke, and height of feeding, grow fierce and <hi>man-keene,</hi> so these Gyants, so much exceeding o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther men in stature and strength, fleshed by oppression of al that lived about them, grew as it were <hi>God-keene,</hi> even to a defiance, at length, of Heaven it self, and as <hi>Salomons</hi> phrase is, to a <hi>falling away in the strength of their foolishnesse,</hi> like the <hi>Behemoth</hi> in <hi>Iob,</hi> that because he could <hi>drinke up the lesser brooks,</hi> he growes confident, <hi>he can drinke up all I<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>rdan into his nostrills,</hi> and therefore <hi>Salomon</hi> begs of God that he would not <hi>give him over to a Gyantlike mind:</hi> If we have not so much strength or power as others, to do our owne wills, let us be content, we have so much the lesse difficulty in doing Gods will, and if we have more then others of this kind of power, let us take heed, least it betray us into the hands of a greater power, that which al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>waies <hi>resists the proud, and giveth grace to the humble,</hi> he hath a dou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble enemy to conquer, whose <hi>power</hi> to do evill is his <hi>wills second.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="2">2. His name <hi>Ishbibenob,</hi> the word signifies an <hi>inhabitant of Nob,</hi> or because of <hi>Nob,</hi> the Sons of God are called <hi>Sojourners</hi> on earth, their <hi>habitation</hi> is in heaven, as Sons of Earth are <hi>inhabitants</hi> here, they have no other heaven. But why of <hi>Nob,</hi> or because of <hi>Nob,</hi> some give this for a reason,<note place="margin">1 <hi>Sam.</hi> 22.</note> that after the Priests were slaine at <hi>Nob,</hi> the Inhabitants degenerated into Gyants, or because the Priests of that God, whose power in <hi>Israels</hi> assistance they had so often felt, being now by <hi>Saul</hi> flaine, these Giants here tooke the greater confi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:50869:5"/> to assault <hi>David,</hi> we see the suppression of Gods servants, or worship by such as should incourage and uphold them, puts confi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence into the enemies of God, to assault his people; there is som<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>what of safety and defence in the residence of Gods Worship, and of such as are faithfull in it, they are the <hi>equites Cataphracti,</hi> the <hi>Horsemen and Chariots of Israel,</hi> even their enemies themselves be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Judges, but we insist not upon names.</p>
            <p n="3">3. His Linage, <hi>Who was of the Sons of the Gyant,</hi> we see of what im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portance it is to be of good Parents, <hi>the son of a Gyant, the son of a wicked woman, the son of a murtherer,</hi> are not only reproaches in Scripture, but reasons why such sons are no better, as <hi>a good sonne makes a joyfull father,</hi> so (ordinarily) a good father makes a happy son, were it but for the love we beare to our children, how much doth it import us to be good? there is not a little in the promise, <hi>I will be a God to thee, and thy seed after thee,</hi> an <hi>Abraham</hi> may have an <hi>Ismael,</hi> an <hi>Isaac</hi> an <hi>Esau,</hi> but generally the promise holds, religious families are the surest nurseries of Religion, the first concoction of grace is ordina<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ily there given, and Physitians tell us, that errors in the first concoction are never well corrected in the second; family neglects of instruction and discipline are seldome supplied in that of the Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gregation or State, there is no so sure an <hi>entayle</hi> as that of vice, it reaches doubtlesse (many wheres) even to <hi>doomesday,</hi> and then how great will that wrath be that is so <hi>treasured up,</hi> and multiplied on still to the very <hi>day of wrath,</hi> and if it will be then so <hi>hard to answer for one of a thousand sins,</hi> how much harder will it be to answer (it may be) one for a thousand souls, that have successively miscarried by a fathers negligence or ill example, Parents do so like snayles on whited walls, guild and make slippery the way they goe, for their chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>drens imitation, and like <hi>Iobs</hi> Leviathan, <hi>make a path to shine after them,</hi> that a <hi>Cain</hi> will not want others <hi>to go on in his way,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Ind.</hi> 11.</note> nor a <hi>Iero<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>boam followers in making Israel to sin.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="4">4. His faternity, <hi>of the sons of the Gyant, or one of the sons of the Gyant,</hi> the <hi>Gyant</hi> had him and many more, <hi>children and the fruit of the wombe, they are an heritage,</hi> (saies the Psalmist) <hi>that cometh of the Lord, of themselves,</hi> they are so, and the choicest of all temporall blessings, and of the best men no lesse passionately desired, <hi>what is all this thou givest me,</hi> (saies <hi>Abraham</hi> to God) <hi>seeing I go childlesse,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Gen.</hi> 15.3.</note>
               <hi>and</hi> Eleazar <hi>of</hi> Damascus <hi>must be mine heire,</hi> and yet wee see (as here)
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:50869:6"/> they often fall plentifully to the share of wicked men, and are their <hi>curses,</hi> and do spread not so much their <hi>name,</hi> as their <hi>guilt,</hi> as (not <hi>mans life</hi>) so, nor doth Gods love <hi>consist in the things which he posses<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ses, mens tables may become snares unto them,</hi> and the <hi>Olive branches about them,</hi> thornes and briars, <hi>i.</hi> curses and vexations; (as with a Nation so) with a family God can <hi>multiply it, and yet not increase the joy,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Esa.</hi> 9.3.</note> all foure of the Gyants sons are found <hi>fighters against God,</hi> and slaine by <hi>David</hi> and his <hi>Worthies,</hi> verse the last.</p>
            <p>The second generall part it is his <hi>Appointment</hi> or <hi>Ammunition,</hi> a great <hi>Speare,</hi> and a <hi>new Sword,</hi> for the Speare, it is like himself, vast and ponderous, the head of it (as most reckon it) neer thirty pound weight, but for the <hi>Sword,</hi> its <hi>newnesse</hi> mentioned, seems to import somwhat of observation.</p>
            <p>The word <hi>Sword</hi> is not expressed in the originall, but in the j<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>dg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of the Translators, supplyed in the word <hi>girt,</hi> it was a <hi>new</hi> one, either because yet <hi>untryed, David</hi> likes the <hi>old</hi> tryed Sword better, that of <hi>Goliah, non</hi> (he saies) to that, <hi>Gyants</hi> &amp; <hi>Tyrants</hi> are all for <hi>new armoury, new devices,</hi> but <hi>experiments</hi> prove alwaies better then <hi>pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>;</hi> when we are able to say with <hi>David, the same God that delivered me out of the claws of the Lyon, and the p<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>es of the Beare, he will de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liver me out of the hands of this insultant Philistin,</hi> the <hi>same Sword that God put into my hand to cut off that his head with, will best de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fend me against Saul:</hi> or <hi>new</hi> .i. <hi>unworne,</hi> unabated in the edge or strength, and then the observation will be, that it is a piece of <hi>gyan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>try,</hi> irreligion, Atheisme, to grow confident on the most likely pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parations and appointments of <hi>great Speares,</hi> and <hi>new Swords,</hi> for a <hi>war: it is the Sword of the Lord and of Gideon,</hi> that will doe it, <hi>Gide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons</hi> Sword without that of the <hi>Lords</hi> before it, making way for it, will prove in the end, but a Lath, a wooden Dagger at the best, hee that can be so confident of his new Sword, as to be content God should be a <hi>Newtrall,</hi> (you know whose speech it was) shall find God a professed enemy before he hath done;<note place="margin">1 <hi>Sam.</hi> 17.47. 2 <hi>Chron.</hi> 20.15. <hi>Dan.</hi> 11. 2 <hi>Sam.</hi> 22.40. <hi>Esa.</hi> 13.4.</note> God will not be made a <hi>Romane Edile,</hi> only to oversee the <hi>Sword play,</hi> no, the <hi>Battell it self it is the Lords,</hi> and least we should understand it in a common notion, or capacity, as all things else are <hi>his,</hi> he pleads his title more distinctly, <hi>the battell is not yours, but the Lords,</hi> and it is he that not only <hi>girds with strength to the battell,</hi> but <hi>musters the Host of the battell,</hi> that <hi>breaketh the Bow, and knappeth the Speare, and burnes the Chariot,</hi>
               <pb n="7" facs="tcp:50869:6"/> without him <hi>Ephraim may be harnessed, and carri<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> bowes,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Psal.</hi> 78.9</note>
               <hi>and yet turn their backs in the battell,</hi> the sword is <hi>commissioned, drawn, whet,</hi> and <hi>bath'd</hi> all in heaven. <hi>Solyman</hi> in counsell about making warre with <hi>Ismael</hi> King of <hi>Persia,</hi> his Bashaw wisely told him, that before he began the war, there were foure great <hi>fountains</hi> to be opened, of <hi>armes</hi> and <hi>victuals, men</hi> and <hi>money:</hi> 'tis true, all must be so, <hi>experi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence shewes it;</hi> but if another <hi>fountain</hi> be not still kept open in hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven, a <hi>fountain</hi> of blessing upon all these foure, they will all prove but <hi>summer brookes,</hi> but <hi>broken cisternes that can hold no water.</hi> And no marvell, that God thus challenges and keeps the di<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>posall of battells more immediately thus in his own hands; for what indeed is <hi>war</hi> other then an <hi>Appeal</hi> and reference to the <hi>umpyrage,</hi> the arbitre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of heaven? and never just,<note place="margin">Justitia in causa, spes in loco salus ex victoria.</note> but when all morall and ordinarie wayes of peace and attonement faile: the Heathen Historian could say, that there were three things necessarily to be consulted in every warre, the <hi>justice</hi> of the cause, the <hi>hope</hi> or likelihood of the under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taking, and the <hi>advantage</hi> of the victorie. The maine, and in the first place, is that of the <hi>justice</hi> of the cause,<note place="margin">
                  <p>Pugnat ni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gra phalanx telum ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rens ore tu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bam{que}: Ipse sibi est telum, dux, hasta, &amp; li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuus.</p>
                  <p>Quin domi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tis de more feris jam Caesar ovâs<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>set:</p>
                  <p>Sed quae ax<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>em traheret musca nec una s<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>it. <hi>Epigr. on Domitians warre with the flies.</hi>
                  </p>
               </note> and for that it can have a warrant no lower then from heaven; and then, in such a warre we may be sure of God for a <hi>reserve</hi> and <hi>second:</hi> and a good cause, a good cal ing to maintaine it, and such a second to assist it, what can resist? In the next place, circumstantiate or advantage a battell never so well with <hi>wind,</hi> and <hi>sun,</hi> and <hi>ground,</hi> and <hi>number,</hi> and <hi>or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der,</hi> unlesse it have all from heaven, the <hi>wind</hi> of the <hi>spirit</hi> in p<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ayer, the <hi>sun of righteousnesse</hi> in faith, the <hi>ground</hi> of hope in promise, the <hi>number</hi> of heavens host in assistance, the order of <hi>Michael and his Angels,</hi> fighting as so many <hi>starres in their courses,</hi> as against <hi>Sise<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ra:</hi> the greater the number, 'tis but <hi>indigesta moles,</hi> so much a grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter heape, and will soone prove so much the greater rout; —<hi>ne<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> quicquam nisi pondus iners,</hi> nothing but a selfe-incumbring lump: and lastly, for the advantage of the victory, if it bring not joy to heaven, and fetch not a blessing thence, it will be but like that of <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lexander</hi> over <hi>Asia, Victor armis, captivus vitiis,</hi> he lost more by the victory, then he won by the warre; or like that of <hi>Domitian</hi> over flies, of whom 'twas well said, that he was <hi>muscis hostis,</hi> and <hi>hostibus musea,</hi> an enemie to flies, and a flie to his enemies: <hi>Bellat<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>r in Theatre,</hi> and <hi>Spectator in Campo,</hi> a souldier on the stage, and a spectator in the field: while we conquer but men, our triumph will
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:50869:7"/> be but over flies, unlesse it be the enemies of heaven we fight against, 'tis but a <hi>stage</hi> triumph that is over any other: if we look unto this our patterne (in the Text) <hi>David,</hi> first for his cause, 'tis God must <hi>plead and avouch it against them that strive against him:</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Psal.</hi> 35.1.43.1.119.154. <hi>Psal.</hi> 3.5.6. <hi>Psal.</hi> 18 29</note> then a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaine for his hope or confidence, if he be not <hi>afraid though ten thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sand should hemme him in,</hi> 'tis because <hi>the Lord sustaines him,</hi> and 'tis <hi>by the helpe of his God that he will leap over the wall,</hi> break through any difficulty; let God never so little withdraw his hand from him, and presently (as he complaines) <hi>fearfulnesse and trembling come upon him, and a fearfull dread overwhelmes him:</hi> so little courage or <hi>heart</hi> hath this <hi>man after Gods own heart:</hi> when God in the least measure leaves him to be his own God, to fight his own battels, and not Gods, he is scarce left to be his owne man. And lastly, for the advantage of the victory, <hi>David</hi> will not think it worth the taking, upon <hi>Shemei,</hi> or <hi>Saul</hi> in the cave, unlesse the glory might redound to heaven.</p>
            <p>We would think it a high peece of madnesse, if being to meet with an enemy in the field, a man should give him the <hi>sword,</hi> and fight himselfe with the <hi>scabberd:</hi> the fullest <hi>Magazine</hi> or <hi>Armou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie,</hi> the greatest, the <hi>newest sword,</hi> though in the hands of an <hi>Ishbi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>benob,</hi> is but an empty scabberd; the sword that turnes the day, its handle is in heaven, there 'tis <hi>drawne,</hi> and <hi>whet,</hi> and <hi>wielded,</hi> there it must be prest and acted by faith and prayer. But I hope, after all the <hi>braying</hi> we have had in this <hi>morter</hi> by the hand of heaven, in the ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny disappointments of our confidence in armes of flesh, we shall hereafter <hi>leave this folly,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Neh.</hi> 4.9.</note> and (with <hi>Nehemiah</hi>) in the first place, <hi>make our prayer unto our God,</hi> and then <hi>set our watch,</hi> make all our preparations to wait upon Gods blessing, with the cripple in the <hi>Acts,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Act.</hi> 3.4.</note> look on <hi>Peter</hi> and <hi>John</hi> as instruments, (they bid him do so) but not <hi>looke so stedfactly on them, as if by their power he had the strength to walke,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Ver.</hi> 12.</note> as they finde fault afterwards.</p>
            <p>His <hi>Designe,</hi> or Councell of Warre, <hi>He thought to have slain David.</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Pro.</hi> 20.18.</note>
               <hi>Every purpose</hi> (saith the Wiseman) <hi>is established by coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sell, and by counsell make warre:</hi> This Gyants <hi>advice</hi> was not <hi>good advice,</hi> God was left out of his counsell, he <hi>thought to have slaine David,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Psal.</hi> 10.4.</note> but <hi>God was not in all his thoughts,</hi> as <hi>David</hi> speakes, and so no marvel if (as the same <hi>David</hi> elswhere) <hi>all his thoughts perish,</hi> and he with them;<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Psal.</hi> 146.4</note> God among other his Titles he stiles himself the <hi>ever<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lasting
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:50869:7"/> Counsellour, the counsell of the Lord</hi> (sayes <hi>David) it will stand,</hi> it is standing counsell, and there is (as he speaks elswhere) <hi>no understanding, nor wisdome, nor counsell that can stand against it,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Pro. <hi>21.30.</hi> Esa. <hi>30.1.</hi> Hos. <hi>8.7.</hi> Concilia callida pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ma specie laeta, tracta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tu dura, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ventu tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stia. <hi>Lib. 35.</hi> Esa. <hi>50.11.</hi>
               </note> nay <hi>woe to them that take counsell, and not of him,</hi> if they do, they do but <hi>sow the wind, and shall reape the whirlewind,</hi> and the reason is there given, <hi>it hath no stalke,</hi> so true is that of the Historian, and a full Commentarie on it is every dayes experience, especially of these last three yeares past, <hi>Dishonest counsells are alwayes in their under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>takings full of hope, in their conducts full of difficulties, and in their issues as full of dangers:</hi> let men <hi>compasse themselves</hi> (as the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phet speaks) <hi>with their owne sparkes,</hi> (and all the vanishing hopes of such counsells are no better) and (as he speaks) <hi>walke in the light of the fire of their own kindling▪</hi> (and what are all such fires but wan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dring <hi>ignes fatui</hi> at the best?) if they will not <hi>heare the voice behind them, saying, this is the way, walke in it,</hi> nor (as he speakes) do not when they are <hi>in darknesse and see no light, stay themselves and their counsels upon their God, this they shall have of his hand, they shall lie down in sorrow:</hi> let them blow their hearts out in the kindling of these their fires, there is a counterblast (the Psalmist speaks of) will make their fires like that of the Prophet,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Esa.</hi> 47.14.</note> where <hi>there shall be n<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>i<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther light to see by, nor cole to warme at,</hi> it is <hi>the blasting of the breath of Gods displeasure;</hi> nay he will (as the Prophet speakes) <hi>make the fire of their own breath to devoure them,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Esa.</hi> 33.11. <hi>Job.</hi> 5.13. <hi>Psal.</hi> 2.2.</note> he will <hi>take the wise in their own craftinesse,</hi> (as <hi>Job</hi> speaks) <hi>and make the counsell of the wicked foolish,</hi> let <hi>Kings band themselves,</hi> and <hi>Rulers take coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sell against the Lord,</hi> he will <hi>laugh them to scorn, the Lord will have them in derision,</hi> it is the <hi>mirth</hi> of heaven as well as the <hi>blisse</hi> of earth▪ to see these fine new devices of wordly polocie and wit, to foole and over-wit themselves first into confidence, then into perplexitie and last of all into shame and scorne, to break the slender thred of their counsells, in the very spinning, by drawing it out into a finenesse.</p>
            <p>And yet this good point of warre, and counsell both, may wee learne from this rude Gyant here; and I would we would learne it, not to be still a arming or taking counsell, untill the enemy recover out of those-straits or wants, to which we have at any time reduced him, the Gyant lets not slip the opportunity of <hi>Davids faintnesse,</hi> he is not then to arme, or consult, or debate his resolution into a losse of the advantage, but as soone as ever he discovers <hi>Davids fainting,</hi>
               <pb n="10" facs="tcp:50869:8"/> then immediately <hi>girt with his new sword he thought to have slai<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e David;</hi> nor did he lose his time or <hi>thought</hi> in thinking, hee sets on him presently; he that is too long a thinking what he hath to do, looses the opportunity of doing what he hath been a thinking. What they say or <hi>Ferne-seed</hi> is no where more true then in opportunities of warre, they bloome, and blossome, and ripen, and fall all many times in one night: <hi>Concilia</hi> (as <hi>Livy</hi> speakes) <hi>dant res hominibus, non homines rebus;</hi> occasions are souldiers counsellours, not soul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diers theirs, <hi>adeò arduum est praescribere,</hi> (as he speaks) so hard is it to prescribe at a distance, <hi>ne que quicquam perniciosius quàm ex alio sapere;</hi> nor is there any thing more dangerous here, then to carry mens braines in other mens heads, the heads and hands in war would by no meanes be at too great a distance.</p>
            <p n="4">4 The fourth and list part 'tis <hi>the Philistins defeat,</hi> and <hi>Davids Reserve, But Abishai the son of Zerviah succoured him.</hi> Be the straits never so great, the enemy never so strong, malicious and cunning, yet if the warre be against Philistins, inveterate enemies to Gods Cause and People, <hi>the Battell</hi> (as well as the Cause) <hi>is the Lords,</hi> and it can never want succours or supplies; some <hi>Reserve,</hi> some <hi>Abishai</hi> or other will be found,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Judg.</hi> 5.20.</note> rather then faile, <hi>The starres in their courses shall fight, and the River Kishon shall sweep them away, that ancient River the River Kishon:</hi> why is God else so often called <hi>the Lord of Hosts?</hi> but that all his creatures in severall <hi>Hosts</hi> fight his Battells, the severall <hi>Hosts</hi> of heaven; Angells against <hi>Senacheribs</hi> great Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>my, <hi>Sun</hi> and <hi>Moone</hi> against <hi>Siserahs,</hi> all the Elements have been se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verally <hi>prest</hi> and <hi>mustered</hi> in this Quarrell, the <hi>Fire</hi> upon the <hi>Troupes</hi> that came to take <hi>Eliah,</hi> the <hi>ayre</hi> in haile-stones upon the <hi>Amorites,</hi>
               <note place="margin">2 <hi>King.</hi> 7.</note> and in a strange and prodigious noise against the great <hi>Syrian Host; Water</hi> against the <hi>Aegyptians,</hi> and rather then faile, the dust of the <hi>earth</hi> shall start up, into <hi>Armies</hi> of <hi>Lice,</hi> and <hi>Flies,</hi> and <hi>Frogs,</hi> against <hi>Pharoh:</hi> Nay, this quarrell shall arme those the most contemptable of all creatures, <hi>Lice,</hi> not only to the terrifying of King <hi>Pharoh,</hi> but to the vanquishing of King <hi>Herod</hi> in the midst of all his guards and glories; we are apt to be startled and plannet-struck at every breath of ill newes, and with those Infidell Murmur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers of <hi>Israel,</hi> presently to question Gods being among us, that one expresse of good newes, in the Prophet <hi>Isaiah</hi> (had wee but hearts to entertain it) <hi>tell Syon that her God raigneth,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Esa.</hi> 52.7.</note> were able to quiet
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:50869:8"/> our spirits in the midst of all rumours, dangers, or losses, whatever: it was the brag of <hi>Caesar</hi> upon the mutiny of his souldiers, that <hi>the fate of Caesar could never want an Army;</hi> he told the Pilot that he need not feare a wrack, <hi>he carried Caesar and his fortunes:</hi> here 'tis no brag, but a solid impregnable truth, the interests of the <hi>Church,</hi> wherein the concernments of Gods <hi>Name, honour, truth,</hi> together with that of the <hi>Kingdom</hi> of his <hi>Son,</hi> can never want an Army; the fraught here secures the vessell, with all the passengers: <hi>Christ</hi> is in the <hi>ship,</hi> and if he seeme to <hi>sleepe</hi> in the midst of the <hi>storme,</hi> 'tis but that we should (with his Apostles) awaken him with our louder cries and prayers, he is that <hi>Rock</hi> upon which this <hi>house of his is built,</hi> the flouds may beat, and breake themselves into froth, they cannot shake it, he it is that is <hi>that hiding place,</hi> in the Prophet,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Esa.</hi> 32.2.</note>
               <hi>the shadow of a mighty rock in a weary Land,</hi> (our Land is just such a one) and he <hi>that dashes against this Rock shalbe broken in pieces, but on whom it shall fall</hi> (as he speakes) <hi>it shall grind him to powder,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Luk.</hi> 20.18</note> (that is) he that comes under this rock under pretence of shelter, and di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>strusts it, it shall fall with more weight on him, then on him that dashes at it in bare enmity; and good reason, such a one is guilty of no lesse then three severall treasons against it, he betrayes the cause to scorne, himselfe to ruine, and God himselfe to the reproach of an unworthinesse to be trusted, an ignoblenesse that every ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nest man disdaines, the not bearing out (to the utmost of what he can) such as he hath put a worke in his service: Let us rather say to God, with that ancient holy man, <hi>Thou altar, th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>n anchor of my soule, let me but serve and trust thee, I aske no more, I will not spend my thoughts upon safety or supplies, to the other two thou givest those without asking.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But what doth <hi>David</hi> in this strait? he <hi>faints,</hi> (saith the Text) but he <hi>flies</hi> not tho', he keeps the field still, he turns not his back upon God, or his cause, he makes no dishonourable peace or truce; I make no doubt of your following him herein. But I hasten to the <hi>Appli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation,</hi> and that in a twofold way, first, by way of <hi>Parallell,</hi> and then of <hi>Direction.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>By way of <hi>Parallell,</hi> or looking our selves in this <hi>glasse,</hi> first; and here I must premise one thing, that <hi>David</hi> in fighting Gods bat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tells is a type of no earthly King, but a type or rather embleme of Gods Church in all succeeding ages, so much the <hi>House of David,</hi> and <hi>Tabernacle of David</hi> doe frequently import in Scripture.</p>
            <pb n="12" facs="tcp:50869:9"/>
            <p>How often hath that <hi>Ishbibenob</hi> of <hi>Rome,</hi> the sonne and heire of all the tyranny and malice of all those former Gyants, <hi>Romes</hi> persecu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting Emperours, how hath he with these Gyant <hi>Phylistins,</hi> againe and againe,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Vers.</hi> 15.</note> and <hi>moreover yet againe,</hi> with his <hi>long great Speare</hi> of <hi>Balaamitish</hi> curses, and his <hi>new Sword</hi> of censures, set upon this our <hi>David,</hi> Gods Church and Cause among us, and that in all times, e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>specially of its straights and <hi>faintings;</hi> one Sword will not serve his turne, <hi>behold two Swords,</hi> a <hi>new</hi> one hath been girt to him by his Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nonists, that of a <hi>universall temporall power,</hi> to that other of his <hi>spiri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuall: Luther</hi> broke so the wards of that his <hi>key</hi> of Purgatory <hi>indul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gences,</hi> that it would serve no longer, so easily to open the peoples pu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ses, as before: and his <hi>Canonists</hi> have beaten it out to him into a <hi>new Sword of Temporall power.</hi> It was the scoffe of a great and wise man, and one of his Church too, who said, <hi>hee liked well of this new Sword of temporall power, in the Popes hand, for as it fares with your quarrelsome Gallants, it is fit they should alwaies have a blunt ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stinado at hand, it many times prevents the drawing of their Swords,</hi> so he thought this <hi>blunter bastinado of Temporall power, would save the Pope a labour of so often drawing out the Sword of his spiritu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all power in censures.</hi> But how often (I say) hath this vaunting <hi>Ish<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bibenob,</hi> with this <hi>new</hi> one of Temporall, and that other <hi>Sword</hi> too, in his invasions and excommunications set upon this our <hi>David,</hi> Gods true Church in this Land?</p>
            <p>In 88. how did he (girt with the new Sword of that vast Arma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>do) think to have taken us in a <hi>fainting</hi> fit, and (with <hi>Ishbibenob</hi> to <hi>David,</hi> as the <hi>Rabbins</hi> fable the story) have tossed us upon that his great Speare of excommunication, many <hi>new swords,</hi> he then threat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned us with, and <hi>new knives too,</hi> with new inscriptions, <hi>To cut the throats of the English Hereticks,</hi> but did not God furnish us with an <hi>Abishai,</hi> to disappoint him? 'twas their owne confession, that <hi>the Sea, nay God himself, proved in that expedition a ranke Lutheran,</hi> it was the confession of <hi>Philip,</hi> the then King of <hi>Spaine,</hi> that <hi>his Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mado had met with an enemy,</hi> (an <hi>Abishai) he never dreamed of, hee sent it to fight against the English Hereticks, and not against the winds and seas,</hi> how gloriously did God then <hi>send a fire,</hi> (a few fired Ships) <hi>into that Forest of his Carmell,</hi> so that that his <hi>halfe-Moone</hi> hath bin in the <hi>wane</hi> ever since.</p>
            <p>After that, againe behold another <hi>new sword,</hi> and in the hand of the same Romish Gyant still, <hi>a Powder-Plot,</hi> (the occasion of this
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:50869:9"/> our present solemnity) a strange <hi>new sword,</hi> come newly, even hot out of the <hi>forge of hell,</hi> sharpned at <hi>Rome,</hi> and to be sheathed in the bowels of <hi>England,</hi> a <hi>flaming sword,</hi> like that in the gap of Paradise, that would (as that) <hi>have turned every way,</hi> to the driving and keep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing us out of the Gospels Paradise; a Sword, (like that of the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phet <hi>Ieremy</hi>) that would not only <hi>have drunke blood, and eaten flesh, but have reached to the very soul,</hi> that would, <hi>at the very fifth rib,</hi> have <hi>struck through the very loynes of all</hi> at once,
<q>Rem, Regem, Regimen, Regionem, Religionem;</q> that would (had it sped) have gone as neer to have reached <hi>Neroes</hi> wish as possible, have made <hi>England</hi> to have but one neck, to strike it off with one blow.</p>
            <p>Nor have we of this age (some of us it may be not then borne) lesse reason still to celebrate the praises of our God, that then sent us so wonderfully an <hi>Abishai</hi> to our succour; for had this sword then reached the blow it aimed at, it would no lesse have reached us, then such as should then have felt it, the Prophet <hi>Ieremie's</hi> devision would then have taken place, <hi>such as were for the sword, to the sword, and such as for the captivity, to the captivity:</hi> we had in all likelyhood bin all made in our better parts, our souls, the miserable spoils and captives, not only to the tyranny, but the Religion of this Romish <hi>Ishbibenob.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>A man would have thought two such <hi>Arbitrements</hi> of heaven had been able to have <hi>non-suited,</hi> and have made them to let fall such a <hi>cause,</hi> so foil'd and blasted; and that malice it selfe would hence<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forward never have recruited any more, but have shrunk back with shame her accursed head into hell and darknesse: no such matter, <hi>moreover still warres with Israel, new swords, new Ishbibenobs</hi> still, in <hi>Ireland, Scotland,</hi> and here among our selves, right <hi>Ishbibenobs,</hi> girt with a <hi>new Array</hi> against <hi>David,</hi> taking all the advantages of his <hi>faintings</hi> upon all occasions: it cannot be denied but <hi>David</hi> a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongst us hath had his <hi>faintings,</hi> Gods providence towards us hath (like a river) many a time seemed weary of its course and channell, and made many a winding about, as if it had lost its way to the O<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cean of his glory, but it hath beene to take in the concurrence and supply of some other streame, to make it run more full and naviga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble, and more able to beare the vessell of his Church and Cause, with deeper bottome and larger sayles, and to contribute more to that sea, and (as it were) the better to take in the succours and supplies of
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:50869:10"/> some <hi>Abishai</hi> or other, to the reliefe of its fayntings. Our <hi>solemne League and Covenant,</hi> together with that free and full assistance from our Brethren of <hi>Scotland,</hi> in pursuance of it, what were they but such <hi>streames</hi> (as it were) taken in to fill this channell of provi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence, which did thus winde about to receive and meet them? what other then so many <hi>Abishai's,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Abishai was Davids si<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sters sonne.</note> sons of our sister Nation, to succour and relieve our <hi>Davids faintings,</hi> I dare say, he is neither true Protestant, nor true English-man, that ownes not God in ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther of those his Titles, <hi>King of Saints,</hi> and <hi>King of Nations,</hi> that doth not with all thankfulnesse and admiration look upon the great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nesse of that contribution which these concurrent streames bring to both those interests of Church, and Nation, by his gracious conduct, who is King of both: For my part, I confesse I could never looke upon that our sister Nation, from their first comming into this King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome, but as a pledge and instrument a tuning in Gods hand, with purpose to worke much more good by, then what <hi>Adrians</hi> wall or <hi>Twede</hi> should be the Southerne bounds of; God usually suits and fits his instruments to his ends, and (me thinks) so admirable a <hi>unity</hi> with so much of <hi>courage, dexterity,</hi> and <hi>discipline</hi> of warre, wonne with so much travell abroad, and put in practice with so much exactnesse at home, by that Nation, even to the matching, (in the last of them) if not exceeding, what we have in story of <hi>Romes</hi> first <hi>Consulate,</hi> seemes not in the usuall course of Providence inten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded to be confin'd to the interest of that one <hi>Kingdome,</hi> (me thinks) it seemes to whisper to a Protestant English spirit, that <hi>Scotland</hi> shall helpe <hi>England,</hi> so as both may not only be able to recover <hi>Ire<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land,</hi> but relieve <hi>Germany;</hi> that their own <hi>issues of bloud</hi> all stancht, they may be able to <hi>give bloud to her to drinke that (drunk with the bloud of the Saints)</hi> is so much the more <hi>thirsty</hi> still, and therefore still yet <hi>makes the Kings of the earth thus drunk with the cup of her fornications,</hi> thereby to enrage them the more to fight her quarrells.</p>
            <p>And for the civill interests of this our Nation, how much of se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>curity and assurance these <hi>streames</hi> of our <hi>mutuall Covenant,</hi> and a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctuall ingagement and assistance do let in, to the filling of that <hi>chan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nell of providence,</hi> there can be no English heart that apprehends not with as much thankfulnesse as joy; this last union in <hi>one Covenant,</hi> is that which crowns all the former three: the union of the Nati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, first, into one <hi>Island,</hi> then in one <hi>Confession,</hi> and last in one <hi>King,</hi>
               <pb n="18" facs="tcp:50869:10"/> were but formall livelesse contiguities at most, until this fourth union in <hi>one Covenant</hi> acted, animated, and spirited them: we have here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by, not onely the old back-doore barr'd, to the prevention of taking cold at our backs, as we were usually subject to, when we had (at any time) <hi>France</hi> an enemy at our faces; but we have now (here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by) a wide doore of hope, or rather security, for a free intercourse in all mutuall supplies of brotherly assistance opened to us: not one<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly a security from dangers, but a supply of all succours upon all oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>casions, insomuch as (I believe) we may without presumption say with <hi>David, Now we know that God out of very faithfulnesse cau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sed us to be troubled, and that Davids fainting in the North so happi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly occasioned the succour of this Abishai; that it was well for us that we were so afflicted, for thereby we have learned and understood the loving kindnesse of the Lord;</hi> it was a happy <hi>wound</hi> that did let out such an <hi>Aposteme</hi> of corrupt festered blood, and found the bot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tome of the <hi>Vlcer.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>I speak not this, to diminish any thing of the merit or successe of those English Northerne <hi>Abishai's,</hi> at <hi>Wakefield, Selby, Yorke,</hi> at <hi>Namptwich,</hi> or <hi>Ormschurch</hi> neither, where (by Gods good hand up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on his <hi>Abishai's</hi>) those <hi>Ishbibenob's,</hi> with their new Irish Popish swords, have received no meane defeats.</p>
            <p>Since that, againe in the <hi>West,</hi> in that shrewd <hi>fainting fit</hi> of <hi>Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vid,</hi> how suddenly had <hi>Ishbibenob</hi> gotten a <hi>new sword</hi> againe, a sword out of <hi>Davids</hi> own hand, wherewith he thought to dispatch him at a blow. I cannot tell ye why that <hi>Abishai</hi> that was sent to <hi>Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vids</hi> reliefe fell short of reaching it; but however, an <hi>Abishai</hi> was not long wanting to <hi>Davids succour,</hi> and <hi>Ishbibenobs</hi> defeat, onely we cannot say, as 'tis here in the Text, that he both <hi>succoured Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vid,</hi> and <hi>slew the Philistine.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But a word of <hi>Direction,</hi> and from this passage in the Text one<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, and that in foure Rules. Would we not want an <hi>Abishai</hi> to suc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cour <hi>David</hi> in any of his <hi>faintings?</hi> then (as here) 1. Do <hi>Justice.</hi> 2. Shew <hi>Mercy.</hi> 3. Maintaine a <hi>correspondency</hi> of succours. 4. Give all the <hi>praise</hi> and <hi>glory</hi> to <hi>God.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="1">1 Do <hi>justice</hi>
               <list>
                  <item>1 To the <hi>meanest.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>2 Vpon the <hi>greatest.</hi>
                  </item>
               </list>
            </p>
            <p n="1">1 To the meanest, though but <hi>Gibeonites,</hi> but <hi>hewers of wood,</hi> and <hi>drawers of water,</hi> as <hi>David</hi> here doth, <hi>He called the Gibeonites, and
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:50869:11"/>
                  <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                     <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb n="18" facs="tcp:50869:11"/>
                  <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                     <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb n="16" facs="tcp:50869:12"/>
                  <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                     <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb n="18" facs="tcp:50869:12"/>
                  <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                     <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb n="16" facs="tcp:50869:13"/> said,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Ver.</hi> 2.</note>
               <hi>What shall I do for you?</hi> he did not stay till their hands and eyes had worne, and wept out their Petitions, and their attendance had made both hands and eyes to faile; no, <hi>Justice</hi> as she hath a <hi>bal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lance</hi> to weigh the cause, so she hath a <hi>sword,</hi> as well to cut off <hi>de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>layes,</hi> as <hi>offences:</hi> these poore <hi>Gibeonites</hi> they had the <hi>publike faith of Israel,</hi> in a Covenant made with them, and if there be any such, (as they say there be very many) I meane such as (may be) their husbands, fathers have lost their lives in the States service, and they them, or are otherwise distressed, and have nothing to support them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>selves &amp; children with, but (may be) a just debt owing by the State, O turne not your eares away from the complaints of these poore <hi>Gibeonites,</hi> remember the counsell of the Prophet to the widdow, <hi>Goe thy way, sell what thou hast, pay what thou owest, and live of the rest;</hi>
               <note place="margin">2 <hi>Sam.</hi> 23.15. 1 <hi>Sam.</hi> 20.14.15.17.41.42.</note> account such a debt, as <hi>David</hi> did, the <hi>water of the Well of Bethlehem,</hi> the <hi>blood of those men that gained it,</hi> do as <hi>Jonathan</hi> to <hi>David,</hi> keep Covenant, though to the <hi>losse of a kingdome,</hi> of a <hi>fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther:</hi> I confesse private interests must give way to the publike, but the faith of the Kingdome past, though but to <hi>Gibeonites,</hi> is the Kingdomes most publike interest of all other; you may plucke downe a mans house, drowne his land for the publike safety, how<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever pluck not down the throne of justice, that were to drown the land in a double floud of its own teares and bloud.</p>
            <p n="2">2 <hi>Vpon the greatest: Sauls sons</hi> are not here spared, no nor may <hi>Agag</hi> or <hi>Benhadad,</hi> though themselves Kings; the sparing of the one of them cost <hi>Saul</hi> his <hi>Kingdome,</hi> and of the other it cost <hi>Ahab</hi> his <hi>life;</hi> nay in the execution of justice upon delinquents, we see in that of <hi>Benjamin</hi> opposing it,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Judg.</hi> 20.</note> a whole Tribe in <hi>Israel</hi> must not weigh against it: <hi>Zimri</hi> and <hi>Cozbi,</hi> though Princes of their peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Numb.</hi> 25.12. <hi>Exod.</hi> 32.29.</note> must be pursued into their <hi>Tents,</hi> their strongest closets, refuges from justice, and <hi>struck through</hi> before the <hi>plague will cease:</hi> this is the way to <hi>consecrate your hands to God,</hi> (as <hi>Moses</hi> speaks) who durst not, we see there, so much as pray for the people, untill an ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ecution of 3000. men, upon that idolatry, had approved him as well a champion of Gods, as an advocate of theirs.</p>
            <p n="2">2 <hi>Shew mercy:</hi> Shew mercy, saies the Wiseman, <hi>unto the li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving, and from the dead with-hold it not; David</hi> doth so here, <hi>he brought up from thence the bones of Saul, and the bones of Jonathan, and gathered the bones of them that were hanged,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Vers.</hi> 13, 14</note> —<hi>and after that
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:50869:13"/> God was intreated for the land: bis vicit qui pepercit,</hi> he hath twice conquered that hath spared: <hi>posse &amp; nolle est nobile,</hi> in some cases, to be able, and yet not to take a revenge, 'tis truly noble: but your mercy, whether in forgiving, or giving, I presume not to think it needs any spurre, only <hi>Livy's</hi> observation would not be forgotten, that it is one of the <hi>Prognosticks</hi> of a <hi>declining State,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Homines quos flagiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>um, egestas, aut conscius animus agi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tabat. <hi>Salust. of Catilines Adherents.</hi>
               </note> to <hi>reward</hi> by <hi>pardoning,</hi> and <hi>punish</hi> onely by <hi>dis-imploying,</hi> when pardons of new offences are made the rewards of old services; and onely dis-im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ployments from future Offices, are made the punishments of past faults: the first makes traitors bold, the second leaves malecontents able to do mischiefe.</p>
            <p n="3">3. <hi>Maintaine correspondence of aid among your forces,</hi> see that your <hi>Abishai</hi> be as neer at hand, and ready upon command, to suc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cour your <hi>Davids</hi> faintings, as these <hi>Ishbibenobs</hi> will be sure to be, to take their advantage of them. When <hi>David</hi> faints, and <hi>Ishbibenob</hi> is ready with his <hi>new sword to stay him; Abishai</hi> (here) acquarrells not his Commission, or disputes not his opportunity till his rescue be too late, but is as ready with his <hi>ward,</hi> as the Gyant is with his <hi>blow,</hi> and truly if <hi>Abishai</hi> be not willing to help <hi>David,</hi> when he may, I know no reason why he should be esteemed and dealt with other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wise, then as a greater enemy to <hi>David</hi> then <hi>Ishbibenob</hi> himself, he is of the two the fairer enemy by farre, that takes his advantage,<note place="margin">
                  <p>Primae im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perandi spes in arduo ubi quis ingres<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sus est, ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sunt studia et ministri. <hi>Tac. Anal, l. 4.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Satius est judicans pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trem forti fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lio quàm pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>triam ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>temperandi exemplo ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rere. <hi>Valer. l. 2. c. 2.</hi>
                  </p>
               </note> then he that betrays his trust; it was the <hi>Romanes</hi> answer to the <hi>Graecians,</hi> boasting of his seven <hi>liberall Arts,</hi> that the <hi>Romanes</hi> had two arts, that were worth all their seaven, <hi>viz. the arts of commanding, and of obeying;</hi> maintain these arts, and they will maintain you: <hi>Tacitus</hi> tels you, <hi>they are somwhat difficult at first, but studied &amp; practised, they be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come as easie as they are safe and usefull.</hi> I mean not such a rigidity of discipline as that of <hi>Chrisantha</hi> in <hi>Xenophon,</hi> so much commended, that having his sword aloft, ready to fal upon the head of the enemy, upon the sound of a retreat, withdrew his blow to the haza<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>d of his owne life. I presse not the severity of <hi>Manlius</hi> putting to death his Son, after his victory, because he had gotten it against command, judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing it (as <hi>Valerius</hi> relates it) safer he should loose so valiant a Sonne, then the Common-wealth should gaine so dangerous an example of disobedience, onely I make bold from this example of <hi>Abishai's succouring faynting David,</hi> to put you in mind that the correspon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dency of your aid, and authority of your commands, once gone, there
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:50869:14"/> will quickly remaine little more then <hi>magni nominis umbra,</hi> such a State, much what like that Parthian Embassy, put into the hands of two, whereof the one was troubled with the Megrim, the other with the Gout▪ of which <hi>Cato</hi> gave his sentence, that the <hi>Embassy had neither head nor foot.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="4">4 <hi>Give all the succours or successes to God—then</hi> David <hi>spake the words of this song,</hi> Let <hi>Abishai's</hi> have their incouragements, rewards, so we shall not want them when there is need, but let God have the praise and glory, so we shall be yet more sure, either to have them, or not to need or misse them, <hi>let us</hi> (with David) <hi>sing our songs unto the Lord,</hi> so shall we not be <hi>driven</hi> (with those in the Prophet) <hi>to howle upon our beds,</hi> let us <hi>bind our Sacrifices to the horns of this altar, so shall we not need to imbrace the rocke for shelter,</hi> but let us <hi>wash our hands in innocency, and so compasse this Altar,</hi> and not only <hi>sing, but live to the praise of his grace, who hath so graciously remembred our</hi> David <hi>in all his troubles.</hi> To whom be praise and glory, &amp;c. <hi>Amen.</hi>
            </p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            <pb facs="tcp:50869:14"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>